Guide to the ILGWU. Sol Chaikin papers,
ILGWU. Sol Chaikin papers,
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives, Cornell University Library
ILGWU. Sol Chaikin papers, 1940-1986
5780/083
Chaikin, Sol C.;International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.
58 linear feet
Records
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives, Cornell University Library
The Sol Chaikin papers document Chaikin's tenure as president of the ILGWU from 1975 to 1986. Included in this collection are extensive correspondence, memoranda, and notes by and to Chaikin from ILGWU officers, staff, and members, politicians, and other labor leaders. Also included are transcripts of Chaikin's speeches, delivered to audiences of local union members, ILGWU and other international union conventions, United States Congress, international labor organizations, and others.
56 cubic feet
The International Ladies’ Garment Workers’ Union was founded in New York City in 1900 by mostly Socialist immigrant workers who sought to unite the various crafts in the growing women's garment industry. The union soon reflected changes in the sector and rapidly organized thousands of unskilled and semi-skilled women, mostly Jewish and Italian young immigrants. Exemplifying the “new unionism,” the ILGWU led two of the most widespread and best-known industrial strikes of the early Twentieth Century: the shirtwaist makers’ strike of 1909 in New York City and the cloak makers’ strike of 1910 in Chicago. The union also tried to adapt to the fragmented and unstable nature of the industry. It adopted the “protocol of peace,” a system of industrial relations that attempted to ensure stability and limit strikes and production disruption by providing for an arbitration system to resolve disputes.
The ILGWU exemplified the European-style social unionism of its founding members. They pursued bread and butter issues but provided educational opportunities, benefits, and social programs to union members as well. In 1919, the ILGWU became the first American union to negotiate an unemployment compensation fund that was contributed to by its employers. The ILGWU also pioneered in the establishment of an extremely progressive health care program for its members which included not only regional Union Health Centers but also a resort for union workers, known as Unity House. The Union also had an imaginative and pioneering Education Department which not only trained workers in traditional union techniques, but provided courses in citizenship and the English language.
David Dubinsky, an immigrant from Belarus who came to the US in 1911, provided strong leadership that led to unprecedented growth in the union during his presidency from 1932 to 1966. He led the union through successful internal anti-communist struggles, built on the ascendancy of industrial unionism by encouraging the formation of the Committee for Industrial Organization, and helped the union become an important political force in New York City and state politics, and in the national Democratic Party and Liberal Party as well.
In the period following the Second World War, the union suffered a decline in membership as manufacturers avoided unionization and took advantage of less expensive labor by moving shops from the urban centers in the northeast to the south, and later abroad. The ethnic and racial character of the ILGWU also changed as European immigrants were supplanted by Asians, Latin Americans, African- Americans, and immigrants from the Caribbean.
In July 1995 the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) at a joint convention, forming UNITE (Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees). At the time the new union had a membership of about 250,000 in the United States, Canada, and Puerto Rico.
1918 Born, New York City, January 9th
1934 Graduated Townsend Harris Hall High School
1940 LL.B Degree, Brooklyn Law School Married Rosalind Bryon Organizer, ILGWU Local 178, Fall River, Massachusetts
1942 Business Agent, Local 281, Boston and Lowell, Massachusetts
1943 U.S. Air Force
1946 Manager, Local 22, ILGWU, Springfield, Massachusetts Manager, Western Mass. District, Northeast Dept., ILGWU
1955 Director, Lower Southwest Region, ILGWU
1959 Vice-President ILGWU
1965 Vice-President ILGWU
1968 Chairman, American Trade Union Council for Histadrut
1969 Associate Trustee, Long Island Jewish Hillside Medical Center
1973 General Secretary-Treasurer, ILGWU Vice-President, AFL-CIO Industrial Union Dept. Member, Board of Directors, New York Urban Coalition
1975 President, ILGWU Vice-President, AFL-CIO and Member, Executive Council Member, Governor's Task Force on Housing
1976 Delegate to Democratic National Convention National Chairman, Trade Union Council for Histadrut
1977 Labor Representative, Belgrade Conference to Review Helsinki Accord on Human Rights Head of AFL-CIO Delegation to International Labor Summit, London Received Labor Human Rights Award, Jewish Labor Committee
1978 Received Townsend Harris Award Member, U.S. Delegation to Attend Funeral of Prime Minister Golda Meir
1979 Present at Signing of Israel-Egypt Peace Treaty at the White House
1980 Member, U.S. Delegation to ILO Session in Geneva Vice-Chair, N.Y. Convention Center Operating Corp. Member, Board of Trustees, Brandeis University Honorary Degrees from Rutgers University and City University of New York Seconded the Nomination of President Carter, Democratic National Convention Published, A Labor Viewpoint: Another Opinion
1982 Head, AFL-CIO Fact-Finding Mission to South Africa Member, N.Y.S. Governor's Special Transit Advisory Panel
1983 Sol C. Chaikin Chair Established at Brandeis University Addressed AFL-CIO Annual Civil Rights Conference Led Import Rollback Campaign
1985 Hosted ZENSEN Delegation from Japan for Discussions of Apparel and Textile Industries
1986 Retired as President of the ILGWU
1991 Died April 1, 1991 at age 73.
The Sol Chaikin papers document Chaikin's tenure as president of the ILGWU from 1975 to 1986. Included in this collection are extensive correspondence, memoranda, and notes by and to Chaikin from ILGWU officers, staff, and members, politicians, and other labor leaders. Also included are transcripts of Chaikin's speeches, delivered to audiences of local union members, ILGWU and other international union conventions, United States Congress, international labor organizations, and others.
Chaikin, Sol C.; Chaikin, Sol C.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Southeast Region
Women's clothing industry--United States; Clothing workers--Labor unions--United States.; Clothing workers--United States.
The ILGWU Records, except for publications and materials produced for publication, are restricted. Materials created prior to twenty years from the current date are open to researchers only with prior written permission from the Director of the Kheel Center; materials created during the past twenty-years are closed; the minutes of the General Executive Board are closed. For more information contact the Kheel Center.
5780. ILGWU records
5780/083 P. ILGWU. Sol Chaikin photographs
5780/135. ILGWU. Sol C. Chaikin. The First Year, 1975-1976. Presentation Volume.
"Permanent deposit"
This collection is divided into fifteen series: General Executive Board Files; Department Files; Regional Department Files; Joint Boards; Councils (Joint and District); Local Files; Reports; General Correspondence; Subject Files; Speeches; Financial Records; Publications; Photographs; Miscellaneous (tapes, memorabilia, etc.); Additional Papers (received after Mr. Chaikin's death).
Series I. General Executive Board Files, 1956-1986
Series II. Department Files, 1942-1986
Series III. Regional Departments, 1938-1986
Series IV. Joint Boards, 1956-1984
Series V. Councils (Joint and District), 1950-1986
Series VI. Local Files, 1969-1986
Series VII. Reports, 1967-1985
Series VIII. Correspondence, 1953-1991
Series IX. Subject Files, 1970-1991
Series X. Speeches
Series XI. Financial records
Series XII. Publications
Series XIII. Photographs
Series XIV. Miscellaneous
Series XV. Additional Papers
- Series I. General Executive Board Files, 1956-1986
  Includes minutes, reports, background materials for reports, meeting announcements, Mr. Chaikin's schedules, notes, and correspondence arranged in chronological order.
  - GEB Files., 1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - GEB Files., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - GEB Files., 1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - GEB Files., 1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - GEB Files., 1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - GEB Files., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - GEB Files., 1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - GEB Files., 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - GEB Files. [folder 1 of 2], 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - GEB Files. [folder 2 of 2], 1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - GEB Files., 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - GEB Files., 1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - GEB Files., 1979 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - GEB Files., 1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - GEB Files., 1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - GEB Files., 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - GEB Files., 1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - GEB Files., 1985 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - GEB Files., 1986 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Series II. Department Files, 1942-1986
  Includes internal department files, arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Archives. [folder 1 of 2], 1973-1986 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Includes excerpts of Cloak Joint Board meeting (4/2/73) regarding the establishment of a central archives; correspondence regarding archives project with Henoch Mendelsund, Director of Archives and Robert Lazar, Archivist.
  - Archives. [folder 2 of 2], 1973-1986 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Auditing Department. [folder 1 of 2], 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Includes printout of liquidated damages collected by Health and Welfare Funds, 1985; correspondence and statistical and financial information.
  - Auditing Department. [folder 2 of 2], 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Collection Control Department, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Documents re the establishment of this department; correspondence and memoranda concerning collection procedures and activities of the department.
  - Data Processing Center, 1976-1981 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Includes financial statement, annual report (1981) and miscellaneous.
  - Education Department, 1977-1985 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Correspondence regarding ILGWU scholarship, educational programs, staff training and related routine.
  - Education Department. College Institutes, 1976-1983 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    re seminars, training institutes and various projects and programs.
  - Education Department. Training Institutes, 1976-1984 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Correspondence re CCNY Internship Program, training institutes and organizing school.
  - International Relations Department. [folder 1 of 2], 1976-1986 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Reports, correspondence, articles regarding foreign labor issues, activities and visits.
  - International Relations Department. [folder 2 of 2], 1976-1986 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Legal Department. Case Files. Belt Firms (NLRB). [folder 1 of 2], 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Legal Department. Case Files. Belt Firms (NLRB). [folder 2 of 2], 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Legal Department. Case Files. Bernie Cowan, Inc. (NLRB), 1975 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Legal Department. Case Files. California Schiffli (NLRB), 1977 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Legal Department. Case Files. Celms, Anna (NLRB), 1975 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Legal Department. Case Files. Charles Sportswear (NLRB), 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Legal Department. Case Files. D and M (NLRB), 1975 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Legal Department. Case Files. Frank Lee (NLRB), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Legal Department. Case Files. Miranda, Berta, 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Legal Department. Case Files. Pier, Jean (NLRB). [folder 1 of 2], 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Legal Department. Case Files. Pier, Jean (NLRB). [folder 2 of 2], 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Legal Department. Case Files. San Francisco Joint Board (NLRB), 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Legal Department. Case Files. Miscellaneous. (NLRB), 1977 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Legal Department. Impartial Chairman Files. Los Angeles Joint Board. [folder 1 of 4], 1971-1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Legal Department. Impartial Chairman Files. Los Angeles Joint Board. [folder 2 of 4], 1971-1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Legal Department. Impartial Chairman Files. Los Angeles Joint Board. [folder 3 of 4], 1971-1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Legal Department. Impartial Chairman Files. Los Angeles Joint Board. [folder 41 of 4], 1971-1977 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Legal Department. General Files, 1942-1967 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Correspondence between law firm of Roewer and Reel and Max Chansky, General Organizer re War Labor Board regulations, labor contracts, collective bargaining issues and other matters.
  - Legal Department. General Files, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Correspondence re department salaries and request for information on the number of ILG members that are Italian-American
  - Legal Department. General Files, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Related routine.
  - Legal Department. General Files, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Correspondence re Kellwood Co. vs. Stulberg, et al, (case); correspondence and brochure concerning a seminar on avoiding unionization; miscellaneous correspondence re staffing the department; copy of letter to George Meany from David Fitzmaurice, President, International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers re new chairman for the NLRB being a "friend" to working people.
  - Legal Department. General Files, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Correspondence with law firms concerning their services to ILG including Eric B. Chaikin, son of President Chaikin.
  - Legal Department. General Files, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Correspondence re political check off contributions; memo regarding charges of unlawful discrimination; and West Coast legal and organizational situation.
  - Legal Department. General Files, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Correspondence re political contributions to Democratic National Committee; substantial memoranda concerning Fall River Grand Jury subpoenas (Local 178) investigating matters having to do with crimes relating to labor; description of bail bond program; staff salaries; re Right To Work Committee lawsuits; and other related routine.
  - Legal Department. General Files, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Related routine legal correspondence.
  - Legal Department. General Files, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Correspondence re Grand Jury Investigation (Mississippi) of Everett Graham and Mordine Barnes concerning suspicion of fraudulent authorization cards; Montreal Crime Commission investigation; raiding matters; homework; embezzlement of Sickness Disability Funds from Fall River Office and related routine.
  - Legal Department. General Files, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Legal correspondence re contract negotiations and other related routine legal matters.
  - Legal Department. General Files, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    N.Y.S. Division of Human Rights legal documents and correspondence re case of discrimination of Edline St. Hill; homework certification rule; and related routine.
  - Legal Department. General Files, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    re political contributions and related routine.
  - Legal Department. General Files, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Includes opinion and award between Local 600 ILGWU and Splendorform Inc. re employer right to reorganize; memo re "country of origin" rules as applied to imports; and other legal matters.
  - Organization and Field Services, Department of, 1976-1986 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Correspondence from organizers reporting on activities in various locals; seminar on organizing; 12 p. "Report on Non-Cutting Operations," and related routine.
  - OSHA, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Political Department. [folder 1 of 2], 1973-1986 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Correspondence re legislative efforts on various issues; political contributions; legislative conferences; (correspondence generally between President Chaikin and Evelyn Dubrow).
  - Political Department. [folder 2 of 2], 1973-1986 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Research Department. [folder 1 of 2], 1973-1986 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Correspondence and minutes re Committee on Developing American Capitalism; mss. re elimination of duties on imported garments; correspondence re Labor-Industry Coalition for International Trade; Urban Enterprise Zone bill; imports; and reports and summaries of meetings (generally correspondence between Chaikin and Herman Starobin).
  - Research Department. [folder 2 of 2], 1973-1986 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Retiree Service Department. [folder 1 of 3], 1976-1986 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Correspondence re the 20th anniversary of the department; correspondence with retirees concerning programs, concerts and other services and activities provided to retirees; also health care, pension payments and related routine.
  - Retiree Service Department. [folder 2 of 3], 1976-1986 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Retiree Service Department. [folder 3 of 3], 1976-1986 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Staff Retirees. [folder 1 of 4], 1975-1986 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Correspondence with staff re amount of pensions, health insurance and related routine.
  - Staff Retirees. [folder 2 of 4], 1975-1986 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Staff Retirees. [folder 3 of 4], 1975-1986 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Staff Retirees. [folder 4 of 4], 1975-1986 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Staff. Payroll, Insurance, Etc., 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Memos and correspondence re wage increases, beneficiaries, resignations and related routine.
  - Staff. Travel Directives, 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Union Health Center [folder 1 of 3], 1975-1986 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Correspondence re alcoholism project; staffing; health education programs; and with patients re various health related issues; also scattered minutes, financial data and reports.
  - Union Health Center [folder 2 of 3], 1975-1986 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Union Health Center [folder 3 of 3], 1975-1986 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Union Label Department [folder 1 of 3], 1975-1984 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Letters from consumers re quality of garments bearing the union label; correspondence re advertisements, label specifications, promotion of union label; reports and samples of labels used by locals, Joint Boards and departments.
  - Union Label Department [folder 2 of 3], 1975-1984 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Union Label Department [folder 3 of 3], 1975-1984 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Unity House [folder 1 of 3], 1975-1986 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Correspondence re bills to permit slot machines at Unity House; proposal for swimming pool complex; accommodations; business proposition with Wayne Newton International Resorts; and related routine.
  - Unity House [folder 2 of 3], 1975-1986 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Unity House [folder 3 of 3], 1975-1986 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Welfare and Health Benefits Department [folder 1 of 6], 1974-1980 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Includes inquiries and concerns about eligibility from members regarding benefits; department staff concerns and activities; also reports and financial data and other related routine matters.
  - Welfare and Health Benefits Department [folder 2 of 6], 1974-1980 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Welfare and Health Benefits Department [folder 3 of 6], 1974-1980 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Welfare and Health Benefits Department [folder 4 of 6], 1974-1980 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Welfare and Health Benefits Department [folder 5 of 6], 1974-1980 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Welfare and Health Benefits Department [folder 6 of 6], 1974-1980 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Welfare Funds Control Department, 1976-1983 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Series III. Regional Departments, 1938-1986
  Generally consists of members' grievances and complaints and steps taken to resolve them. Issues covered include wages, piece work, holiday pay, retirement eligibility, health insurance coverage, local staffing problems, discharge, lay-off, non union work and others. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Canadian Area, 1973-1986 (Box 4, Folder 1-14)
    Correspondence with Si Bresner, Canadian Director; Gilles Gauthier, President, Quebec Jt. Council and others concerning anti-union articles in Montreal papers; staff salaries; negotiations; organizing in Toronto; Committee of Inquiry formed by Quebec Federation of Labor to assess situation of complaints against ILG (1976); Crime Commission Inquiry (1980) in Montreal; appeals cases; Tan-Jay Co. negotiations; membership decline; benefits; Amalgamated Clothing Workers raiding complaints; resignation of Gilles Gauthier as President of Quebec Jt. Council; 12 p. "Report on the Situation in Quebec," 1986; newsletter and financial data.
  - Central States Region, 1973-1986 (Box 4, Folder 15-31)
    Correspondence with Fred Siems, Director and Glenn Clay, Regional Director re complaints of Local 528, Vandalia, IL.; problems in supplying Girl Scout uniforms; charge of unfair labor practices by Kellwood Co., Little Rock, Arkansas; merger of Kansas City Jt. Board and the Missouri-Kansas-Nebraska-Iowa-Minnesota District Council; case of Minnie Dill re vacation pay; NLRB case re Amalgamated Clothing Workers/ILGWU and Sun Apparel of El Paso, TX.; employee grievances re shops closing, terminations without just cause and others; 17 p. summary of findings and recommendations of Kellwood Mfg. Co., Little Rock, AR (1983) re improvement of productivity and 17 p. report on Martha Manning Co., Little Rock, AR; Local 525, West Helena, AR, petition signed by members requesting Chaikin to look into problems; negotiating problems in Kellwood Co. negotiations (1984); audit, correspondence and contract of Youthcraft Coat and Suit Co. (1984-86), Kansas City, Missouri.
  - Eastern Region [folder 1 of 2], 1974-1978 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    With Edward Krammer, General Manager, Eastern Region. Letter from President of Poirette Inc. re competition from non-union company; Russ Togs having work done in non-union shop during strike; grievances and complaints of members; re Evan-Picone, Inc., agreement and related routine.
  - Eastern Region [folder 2 of 2], 1974-1978 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Eastern Pennsylvania, 1977-1982 (Box 4, Folder 34-41)
    With Director Irwin Solomon re members complaints and grievances; purchase of non-union shops; use of non ILG contractors; crime in the Philadelphia area where the union building is located; 19 p. memo, "Prepaid Legal Services for Members of the Knit Goods Workers Union, Local 190" analyzing whether or not such a plan would be feasible; shops changing workers from time work to piece work; and other related routine.
  - Eastern Pennsylvania [folder 1 of 7], 1983-1986 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    With Earl Laub, Assistant Director and others re distribution and eligibility of vacation checks and other member grievances; firms going out of business and related routine.
  - Eastern Pennsylvania [folder 2 of 7], 1983-1986 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Eastern Pennsylvania [folder 3 of 7], 1983-1986 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Eastern Pennsylvania [folder 4 of 7], 1983-1986 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Eastern Pennsylvania [folder 5 of 7], 1983-1986 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Eastern Pennsylvania [folder 6 of 7], 1983-1986 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Eastern Pennsylvania [folder 7 of 7], 1983-1986 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Midwest Region, 1973-1986 (Box 5, Folder 8-16)
    With Harold W. Schwartz, Director and Lou Montenegro, Director re closing of Glazier Co. in Zion, IL and others; case of employee of KPB Industries writing to George Meany about seniority and being denied union membership; non-ILG contract work; re-opening of Huntington Industries Plant in Benton, IL; complaints and grievances of employees; negotiations with R & M Kaufmann Inc., Smoler Brothers Inc. and Chicago Association; and related routine.
  - New England Region, 1975-1986 (Box 5, Folder 17-31)